[Music]
foreign
I studied more than a thousand food
poisoning outbreaks determined that
poultry specifically chicken was the
most common culprit highlighting the
role of poultry is a major source of
foodborne outbreaks in the United States
fish with second beef was third but
aren't people more likely to order their
burgers rarer than their chicken
sandwich
see the biggest problem isn't the
cooking but the handling both at home
and in the store a shop-along study was
conducted to determine actual shopping
behavior of consumers who purchased raw
poultry products
what did they find neither hand
sanitizer or wipes were observed in 71
percent of grocery store meat sections
of the stores visited and even when they
were there only one participant out of
the 96 they followed used it therefore
it's important to educate Shoppers on
the importance of using hand sanitizer
in the meat section after touching
poultry packages because food poisoning
bacteria can get on the outside of the
package
plastic bags were available in most meat
sections but only a quarter of the
Shoppers used the bags for their raw
poultry purchases the Shoppers just
usually place the poultry directly in
the main basket of the grocery cart
where it could come in contact with
fresh produce that maybe even Raw on a
salad or something
and then where does their hand go they
didn't use any kind of sanitizer and
they then just grabbed the handle of the
cart because they're not practicing good
hand hygiene when handling poultry in
the grocery store meat section they
could contaminate a variety of items as
a result of contact with their hands
touching the cart after directly
handling the Poulter packages could
potentially mean that the cart becomes a
risk factor for salmonella or
campylobacter for the next person the
bacteria potentially left on the cart
could affect other Shoppers not just the
person picking up the poultry so some
kale Shopper following all the safety
precautions can come along and still be
exposed to poultry contamination via the
cart
in addition to touching the cart poultry
Shoppers may also touch a personal item
after touching a raw poultry package a
personal item like their children
after touching poultry packages 31 of
Shoppers touched a personal item like
their purse their child
most left the store with poultry
separated in its own bag however most
consumers then took it out of this
protective layer when they got home and
one in three placed the package directly
on the counter before it went into the
fridge
and most were just put straight in where
it could potentially come in contact
with other items fewer than one in five
consumers correctly stored raw poultry
on the bottom shelf in a sealed
container or plastic bag always in the
bottom since if the raw juices leak they
could contaminate other Foods
the next mistake most people make is
then washing or rinsing raw poultry
before cooking it up to 90 percent of
people say they wash their chicken
before cooking it because that's what
they're used to and they want to rinse
the Slime off the problem is that the
Slime can be splashed throughout like a
two foot Halo of contamination around
the sink a lot of folks heard you
weren't supposed to do that but they
continue to do it anyway
fewer than about one in ten thaw frozen
poultry the way they should in a seal
container plastic bag submerged in cold
water with the water changed every 30
minutes is it better to put raw poultry
on a wood cutting board or a plastic
cutting board neither is safe as they
both get rapidly contaminated
failure to then use a food thermometer
is another potentially unsafe practice
given that 70 of chicken pieces that
were judged by consumers has done had
not reached safe internal cooking
temperatures in focus groups many
participants thought food thermometers
were unnecessary to determine whether
mean poultry was cooked thoroughly
because look they've been cooking for
years without once getting food
poisoning but have they ever got a
24-hour flu there's no such thing as a
24-hour flu that's likely food poisoning
stomach flu or stomach bug that's likely
food poisoning ever had a urinary tract
infection
there are multiple lines of evidence
indicating poultry as a major food
animal reservoir for urinary tract
infection bacteria that lay in weight in
the rectum and then crawl up they're
more than a million foodborne salmonell
and campylobacter infections every year
in the United States
although half of Americans think it's
not very common for people in the United
States to get foodborne illness because
of the way food is prepared in their
home
food safety experts estimate that the
home is the primary location where
foodborne disease outbreaks occur
[Music]
foreign